MUHAMMAD ZIAD ABUSAA

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

+13 years experience of software development and +5 years of experience in DevOps, SRE and Cloud technologies. Well-versed in technology to create systems that are reliable and user-friendly. Skilled leader who has the proven ability to motivate, educate, and manage a team of professionals to build applications and effectively track changes.

WORK HISTORY

SITE RELIABILITY ENGINEERING (SRE) LEAD LUCID MOTORS



I have played a pivotal role in ensuring the reliability, scalability, and performance of our infrastructure and applications. My responsibilities encompassed a wide range of tasks and initiatives, including:

1. Infrastructure as Code (IaC) with Terraform Implementing Infrastructure as Code (IaC) using Terraform, streamlining the provisioning of resources across both AWS and OCI cloud environments

2. Continuous Delivery with Argo CD:

Leveraging Argo CD, I orchestrated and automated our Kubernetes workloads' continuous delivery pipelines. This allowed for more efficient and reliable application deployments while ensuring that the desired state of the cluster was maintained.

3. Monitoring and Alerting:

I took charge of designing and implementing a robust monitoring system for our Kubernetes clusters using the Kubernetes Prometheus stack. This included creating custom metrics and alerts to proactively identify and address issues before they impacted the availability of our services. Grafana was instrumental in visualizing these metrics and enabling rapid response to incidents.

4. Cost Optimization:

I initiated a comprehensive cost optimization strategy across our AWS and OCI environments. This involved identifying idle resources, rightsizing instances, and implementing resource lifecycle management practices, resulting in substantial cost savings for the organization.

5. Leadership and Team Development:

As an SRE Lead, I assumed a leadership role in mentoring and guiding team members, both technically and in their career development. I conducted regular one-on-one meetings, set performance goals, and provided constructive feedback to foster growth and collaboration within the team.

6. Departmental Goals and OKRs:

I played a pivotal role in aligning our SRE team's efforts with departmental goals and Objectives and Key Results (OKRs). By effectively communicating and driving the team's focus towards these objectives, we consistently met and exceeded performance targets.

PRINCIPAL DEVOPS ENGINEER VISION BANK

1/1/2022 - 04-05-2023

- DevOps technologies and tooling selection and implementation.
- 2. Leading Cloud adoption in organization.
- 3. Leading GitOps implementation for applications using Argo CD.
- 4. Shifting security left: implemented security checks such as SAST and SCA in applications pipelines.
- 5. Quality code checks in pipelines using Sonarqube.
- Working closely with our development team to create an automated continuous integration (CI) and continues delivery (CD)
- 7. Implemented monitoring using Prometheus and Grafana stack.

io

- 8. Infrastructure provisioning using Terraform.
- 9. Patching/upgrading tools and packages with latest versions.
- 10. Working closely with Cyber to apply the security requirements in applications and tools.
- Training and enabling new joiners in Platform and DevSecOps areas

PLATFORM LEAD (CLOUD NATIVE APPLICATIONS), THIQAH BUSINESS SERVICES

U

1/9/2019 - 30/12/2021

- 1. Leading software delivery projects for Governments clients (Design and Implementation).
- 2. Leading more than one team that overall consistent +10 people.
- 3. Leading transformation into Cloud native Apps.
- 4. Leading adopting Kubernetes / Containerization in entire company.
- 5. Participate and advise in projects Design/Architecture with Architecture team.
- 6. Adopting Agile, DevOps practices.
- 7. Backend APIs development

PRODUCT MANAGER / TEAM LEAD, NETWAYS, RIYADH



1/1/2018 - 1/8/2019

- Team leader, responsible of project implementation and delivery and managing the dev team / following up on daily basis.
- 2. Reviewing the final product before shipping into customer, In terms of business and technical implementation.
- 3. Product management: responsible of managing product backlogs and first chair customer facing person.
- 4. Participate in application design with Architecture team.

Page | 3 Muhammad Ziad Abusaa

net ays

TECHNICAL TEAM LEADER, NETWAYS, RIYADH

1/1/2017 - 30/12/2017

- Team leader, responsible of project implementation and delivery and managing the dev team / following up on daily basis.
- 2. Developing solutions using NET.
- 3. Building solutions using MS SharePoint.
- 4. Identifying and analyzing system requirements.
- 5. Defining project scope, and preparing analysis document.

SENIOR SOLUTION DESIGNER, NETWAYS, RIYADH



1/12/2012 - 1/1/2017



1/1/2010 - 30/11/2012



PUBLISHED COURSES

Argo CD Essential Guide for End Users (Udemy)





CERTIFICATIONS

AWS Certified Cloud Practitioner

validation #: N9YY5EB2WEEQ1M5Z

PCA: Prometheus Certified

Associate

Certification Number: LF-pp8k8uvy3s

Cloud Digital Leader Certification Number: xvCjoH

CKA: Certified Kubernetes

Administrator

Certification Number: LF-kg8hjq9m42









Page | 4 Muhammad Ziad Abusaa

CKS: Certified Kubernetes Security

Specialist

CERTIFICATION NUMBER: LF-IJ4BDLK3O6

CKAD: Certified Kubernetes Application Developer

Certification Number: LF-4xr63e8hp8

Microsoft Certified: DevOps

Engineer Expert

Certification Number: H584-3759

Microsoft Certified: Azure

Developer Associate

Certification Number: H584-3619

Microsoft® Certified Solutions

Expert: Productivity

Certification Number: G421-5726

Microsoft® Certified Solutions

Associate: Office 365

Certification Number: G421-5525

Microsoft Certified Professional Certification Number: E933-3478















SKILLS

- Containers orchestration / Kubernetes. "CKA, CKS and CKAD"
- Oracle Cloud.
- Google Cloud: Cloud Digital Leader
- Azure DevOps. "Certified"
- DevSecOps.
- Helm Charts: Building and maintaining.
- GitOps: Argo CD
- Teleport for PAM
- Building IaC using Terraform.
- Version control systems such as Azure DevOps and Gitlab.
- Secrets management using Vault
- Observability: Prometheus / Grafana / Alert manager.
- Rancher.

- Team management / leadership
- .NET Core / Framework.
- Client Side Development
- SharePoint "Certified"
- Office 365 Understanding
- CRM Understanding
- BizTalk Understanding
- K2 Understanding
- Angular
- Project Scoping
- Application design
- Preparing demos and related presentation
- Product owner / scrum master / solution management
- System / Business analysis

PROFESSIONAL ACHIEVEMENTS

PLATFORM AND TRANSFORMATION

- Building production ready platform around cloud native ecosystem.
- Building Toolchain for DevSecOps.
 - Git and CI & CD tools.
 - Monitoring tools.
 - Secrets management tools.
 - Security tools for DevSecOps.
- Leading organization transformation using cloud native ecosystem.
- Applying security best practices related to systems, clusters and applications.
- Built multiple k8s clusters managed and "self hosted" for multi environments including production environment.

Page | 6 Muhammad Ziad Abusaa

INTERNET AND ESERVICES PROJECTS

- Amaaly: .NET Core / Docker / Kubernetes.
- Ministry of commerce / Franchise : .NET Core / Angular
- Ministry of commerce / Maroof : .NET Core / Docker and Kubernetes .
- SFDA eservices project : .Net Core , Kubernetes , React
- Ministry of interior Mifon Project : Angular JS , Web Api , SharePoint , CRM
- GMCO internet website : SharePoint 2013 , Word Automation
- The centennial fund eServices website (eServices using .Net)
- Alrajhi Takaful Internet website (eServices using .Net)
- Council of Saudi Chambers Internet website: SharePoint 2010
- High Commission for the Development of Arrivadh website: SharePoint 2010

ERP

RDCCI ERP web application (using asp.net web forms)

INTRANET PROJECTS

- Sanabil Intranet: SharePoint 2016 / CMS
- SASO Intranet: SharePoint 2010 / .Net / AngularJs / K2
- Ecra intranet : SharePoint 2013 / Word Automation
- GMCO intranet : SharePoint 2013 / CMS
- COE enterprise content management system : SharePoint
- Riyadh Chamber of Commerce Intranet : SharePoint 2010

EDUCATION

BACHELOR IN COMPUTER SCIENCE, UNIVERSITY OF JORDAN, AMMAN

2005-2009

Page | 7 Muhammad Ziad Abusaa